Guide to the Al Todres Brooklyn Dodgers Collection BCMS.0052
Brooklyn Collection
Al Todres Brooklyn Dodgers Collection
1928-2010
1940-1960
Center for Brooklyn History
BCMS.0052
2.5 Linear Feet in 3 document boxes, 1 oversize box
Brooklyn Dodgers memorabilia including yearbooks, photographs, magazines and programs.
Access
Collection is located in the Brooklyn Collection at the Central Branch at Grand Army Plaza. The collection may only be used in the library and is not available through interlibrary loan. Requests to view the collection must be made at least 48 hours in advance of visit.
Provenance
This collection was donated by Albert Todres in 2013.
Scope and Contents
This collection is comprised of baseball memorabilia and publications concerning the Brooklyn Dodgers. Materials created on behalf of the Dodgers club such as yearbooks, ticket stubs and programs are included; as well as items about the Dodgers created by other companies, such as magazines and guidebooks. Items created after the team's 1958 move to Los Angeles are included if the content references the Brooklyn years or players, such as obituaries of prominent players, general team histories and honors.
Images include team photos, autographed photos and illustrated postcards. The Dodgers 1941, Today and Yesterday and The Dodger Victory Book were designed by noted abstract painter Ad Reinhardt.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in six series:
Series I: Serials is arranged alphabetically by title.
Series II: Yearbooks is arranged chronologically.
Series III: Photographs is arranged by subject.
Series IV: Clippings is arranged chronologically when possible.
Series V: Ephemera is arranged alphabetically by item.
Series VI: Books and Guides is arranged alphabetically by title.
Related Materials
Articles from the Brooklyn Daily Eagle
Photographs from the Brooklyn Daily Eagle
Stanley Person Baseball Collection
Golenbock, Peter. Bums--an oral history of the Brooklyn Dodgers. Putnam, 1984.
Krell, David. "Our bums": the Brooklyn Dodgers in history, memory and popular culture. McFarland & Company, Inc., Publishers, 2015.
McGee, Bob. The greatest ballpark ever: Ebbets Field and the story of the Brooklyn Dodgers. Rivergate Books, 2005.
Prince, Carl E. Brooklyn's Dodgers: the bums, the borough, and the best of baseball, 1947-1957. Oxford University Press, 1996.
Historical Note
Baseball clubs were introduced to Kings County as early as the 1820s, with over 71 amateur teams playing in the county by 1851. Early prominent clubs included the Atlantics and the Ekfords, drawing players from the blue collar workforce and attracting thousands of fans to games played all over the borough. In 1883, Charles Byrne opened the Washington Park baseball field on 5th Avenue and 3rd Street in Park Slope and formed a team called the Brooklyn Grays. The team joined the American Association in 1884 and the National League in 1890, by which time they were known as the Bridegrooms.
In 1891 Washington Park burned down and the team was moved to Eastern Park, a 12,000 seat stadium in Brooklyn's Brownsville neighborhood. The team was still known as the Bridegrooms but picked up several nicknames including the Superbas and the Brooklyn Trolley Dodgers, named after borough residents who had to "dodge" oncoming electric trollies. In 1898 Byrne died and was succeeded by his assistant, Charlie Ebbets. By 1899 Ebbets gained majority control over the team and in 1912 moved them to Ebbets Field, a new 37,000 seat stadium in Flatbush.
The team played and lost their first World Series game in 1916, in front of the largest crowd in baseball history. By 1920 the team was officially known as the Brooklyn Dodgers, but was also called the Daffiness Boys, a nickname reflective of their performance on the field and outrageous behavior of players and management. The death of Charlie Ebbets in 1925 left the team open to poor management and a series of disastrous trades that led to a drop in ticket sales and a field in need of repairs. Things began to turn around in 1938 when Leland MacPhail was brought in as General Manager. MacPhail got rid of the Daffiness Boys and replaced them with some of the Dodgers' most iconic players, including Pee Wee Reese and Pete Reiser.
When the U.S. entered World War II MacPhail and several players enlisted. Branch Rickey was brought in from St. Louis as the new General Manager. In 1947 he signed Jackie Robinson, the first black man to play on a major league baseball team. The 1947 season kicked off an era often called the "glory days" with star players including Roy Campanella, Duke Snider and Gil Hodges. Brooklyn supported their team with steady game attendance, merchandise sales and their own fight song, "Follow the Dodgers." After years of close-calls and near-misses the team finally captured a World Series title in the 1955 season.
After 43 years Ebbets Field was in a state of disrepair and team owner Walter O'Malley began to make plans for a new stadium in Brooklyn. O'Malley's plan for a city subsidized stadium at the intersection of Flatbush and Atlantic Avenue that would provide more seats, parking and access to public transportation was rejected by Robert Moses, who proposed an alternative location in Queens, the eventual site of Shea Stadium. O'Malley began negotiations with the city of Los Angeles, which promised a growing market and space for a new stadium. The National League authorized the move on May 28, 1957 and the Los Angeles Dodgers played their first game on April 18, 1958.
Baseball teams--United States--History; Baseball--United States--History--20th century; Brooklyn Dodgers (Baseball team); Sports writing
- Series I: Serials
  - Baseball Digest, 1951 (Feb.) (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Baseball Magazine, 1943-1953 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Baseball Magazine, 1953-1957 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Complete Baseball, 1952-1953 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Dell Baseball Annual, 1953-1955 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Dodger Doings, 1941-1943 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Line Drives, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Prologue, 2008 (Spring) (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Sports Illustrated, 1955-1958 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Sport Life, 1951 (Sept.) (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Sport Magazine, 1958 (Jan.) (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Ebony, 1950 (June) (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Life, 1948 (April) (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Series II: Yearbooks
  - Yearbooks, 1949-1952 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Yearbooks, 1953-1957 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Los Angeles Dodgers Bluebook, 1958, 1987, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Los Angeles Dodgers Bluebook, circa 1990-1998 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Series III: Photographs
  - Autographed Photos (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Team Photos, 1928, 1932, 1935 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Series IV: Clippings
  - Clippings, circa 1975-2010 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Clippings (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Series V: Ephemera
  - Score Cards, 1942-1958 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Pin, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Postcards, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Stamp, 2006 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Ticket Stubs, 1955-1956 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - World Series Programs, 1941-1956, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Calendar, 1995 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Pennant, 1955 (Box 4)
- Series VI: Books and Guides
  - Baseball Guide and Record Book, 1943 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Baseball History, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Baseball's Beloved Bums, 1947 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Brooklyn's Best, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - The Dodger Victory Book, 1942 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - The Dodgers 1941, Today and Yesterday (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - The Dodgers, All Time Greats, circa 1975 (Box 3, Folder 13)